A Guide to the J. George Harrar Papers FA046
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Correspondence, 1946-1982; 1; 12.1 Cubic Feet
  - Correspondence - Collateral Interests, 1960-1982; 1_4
    - President's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs, September 1966 (Box 32, Folder 241)
    - President's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs, October-November 1966 (Box 32, Folder 242)
    - President's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs, December 1966 (Box 32, Folder 243)
    - President's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs, January-February 1967 (Box 32, Folder 244)
    - President's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs, March-April 1967 (Box 33, Folder 245)
    - President's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs (The World Food Program) (Box 33, Folder 246)
    - President's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs, May-August 1967 (Box 33, Folder 247)
    - President's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs, September 1967 (Box 33, Folder 248)
    - President's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs, October 1967-September 1968 (Box 33, Folder 249)
    - President's General Advisory Committee on Foreign Assistance Programs, October 1968-June 1969 (Box 33, Folder 250)
    - Projects for Population Action, 1976-1977 (Box 34, Folder 251)
    - Public Welfare Medal, 1963 (Box 34, Folder 252)
    - Puerto Rico Academy of Sciences, 1961 (Box 34, Folder 253)
    - Rockefeller Archive Center, 1973 (Box 34, Folder 254)
    - Rockefeller Archive Center, January-March 1974 (Box 34, Folder 255)
    - Rockefeller Archive Center, April-August 1974 (Box 34, Folder 256)
    - Rockefeller Archive Center, January-June 1975 (Box 34, Folder 257)
    - Rockefeller Archive Center, July-December 1975 (Box 34, Folder 258)
    - Rockefeller Archive Center, 1976 (Box 35, Folder 259)
    - Rockefeller Archive Center, 1978-1981 (Box 35, Folder 260)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1955-1963 (Box 35, Folder 261)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1968-1973 (Box 35, Folder 262)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1974-1977 (Box 35, Folder 263)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1978-1979 (Box 35, Folder 264)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1980-1982 (Box 36, Folder 265)
    - Rockefeller University Council, 1973-1974 (Box 36, Folder 266)
    - Rockefeller University Council, 1974 (Box 36, Folder 267)
    - Rockefeller University Council, 1975-1977 (Box 36, Folder 268)
    - Royal Society of Arts, Manufacturers, and Commerce, 1972 (Box 36, Folder 269)
    - Science Advisor to The President, 1975 (Box 36, Folder 270)
    - Senate Finance Committee Hearing, June-August 1969 (Box 36, Folder 271)
    - Senate Finance Committee Hearing, September 1969 (Box 37, Folder 272)
    - Senate Finance Committee Hearing, September 1969 (Box 37, Folder 273)
    - Senate Finance Committee Hearing, October 1969 (Box 37, Folder 274)
    - E. C. Stakman Award, 1955-1965 (Box 37, Folder 275)
    - E. C. Stakman Award, 1966-1982 (Box 37, Folder 276)
    - "Time" News Tour, 1964-1965 (Box 37, Folder 277)
    - "Time" News Tour, 1965 (Box 37, Folder 278)
    - Treasury Department Report on Private Foundations, 1965 (Box 37, Folder 279)
    - World Academy of Art and Science, 1963-1968 (Box 38, Folder 280)
    - World Food Institute, 1973-1974 (Box 38, Folder 281)
    - Viacom International Inc., 1971-1976 (Box 38, Folder 282)
    - Viacom International Inc., 1977-1980 (Box 38, Folder 283)
  - Correspondence - Relating to Written Materials, 1958-1975; 1_5
    This subseries complements the material in Series 2. Included are acknowledgements from many scientists concerning the Harrar and Stakman book, "Principles of Plant Pathology."
    - "Principles of Plant Pathology", 1957-1958 (Box 38, Folder 284)
    - "Principles of Plant Pathology", 1957-1958 (Box 38, Folder 285)
    - "Principles of Plant Pathology", 1957-1958 (Box 38, Folder 286)
    - "Principles of Plant Pathology", 1957-1958 (Box 39, Folder 287)
    - "Principles of Plant Pathology", 1957-1958 (Box 39, Folder 288)
    - "Principles of Plant Pathology", 1957-1958 (Box 39, Folder 288A)
    - "Principles of Plant Pathology", 1958-1967 (Box 39, Folder 289)
    - Miscellaneous, 1960-1962 (Box 39, Folder 290)
    - Miscellaneous, 1963-1966 (Box 39, Folder 291)
    - Miscellaneous, 1967 (Box 39, Folder 292)
    - Miscellaneous, 1968 (Box 40, Folder 293)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1974 (Box 40, Folder 294)
    - Miscellaneous, 1974 (Box 40, Folder 295)
    - Miscellaneous, 1975 (Box 40, Folder 295A)
    - Miscellaneous, 1976-1981 (Box 40, Folder 296)
- Speeches, Manuscripts and Publications, 1930-1979; 2
  Subseries 1 - Book Manuscripts Subseries 2 - InterviewsSubseries 3 - Publications (and Reprints) Subseries 4 - Speeches Subseries 5 - Miscellaneous Papers
  - Speeches, Manuscripts and Publications - Book Manuscripts, 1958-1979; 2_1
    The subseries is arranged chronologically.
    Subseries 1 contains drafts and outlines of both published and proposed books, including the F. Fowle manuscript entitled "Recollections of J. George Harrar on the Agricultural Program of The Rockefeller Foundation," 1967. Also included are various reviews of "The Principles of Plant Pathology."
    - "Principles of Plant Pathology" - Reviews, 1958 (Box 41, Folder 297)
    - "Principles of Plant Pathology" - Reviews, 1958 (Box 41, Folder 298)
    - Blueprint for Hungry Nations: The Mexican Agricultural Program of the Rockefeller Foundation, 1961 (Box 41, Folder 298A)
    - Book Manuscripts (Box 41, Folder 299)
      Scope and Contents
      Principles and Problems of Technical Assistance and Their Application to the Rockefeller Foundation's Program of Technical Collaboration in Mexico, 1964.
    - Recollections of J. George Harrar On The Agricultural Program of The Rockefeller Foundation, with F. Fowle, 1967 (Box 41, Folder 300)
    - Recollections of J. George Harrar On The Agricultural Program of The Rockefeller Foundation, with F. Fowle - Drafts, 1967 (Box 41, Folder 301)
    - Recollections of J. George Harrar On The Agricultural Program of The Rockefeller Foundation, with F. Fowle - Drafts, 1967 (Box 41, Folder 302)
    - Recollections of J. George Harrar On The Agricultural Program of The Rockefeller Foundation, with F. Fowle - Drafts, 1967 (Box 41, Folder 303)
    - Recollections of J. George Harrar On The Agricultural Program of The Rockefeller Foundation, with F. Fowle - J. Allen Revision, 1969 (Box 41, Folder 304)
    - The Years with the Rockefeller Foundation, 1979 (Box 42, Folder 305)
  - Speeches, Manuscripts and Publications - Interviews, 1949-1978; 2_2
    Subseries 2 contains transcripts of radio and TV interviews relating to agriculture, world hunger, and Harrar's role as President of the Rockefeller Foundation.
    - Miscellaneous, 1949-1969 (Box 42, Folder 306)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1970 (Box 42, Folder 307)
    - Oral History - Rockefeller Foundation Program in Agriculture, 1961 (Box 42, Folder 308)
    - Excerpts - Interview Concerning Mexican Agricultural Program, 1978 (Box 42, Folder 309)
  - Speeches, Manuscripts and Publications - Publications (and Reprints), 1930-1979; 2_3
    This subseries includes a few of Harrar's earliest published scientific articles.
    - Miscellaneous, 1930-1953 (Box 42, Folder 310)
    - Miscellaneous, 1953-1958 (Box 42, Folder 311)
    - Miscellaneous, 1959-1963 (Box 42, Folder 312)
      Includes list of technical publications, 1930-1962.
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1966 (Box 43, Folder 313)
    - Miscellaneous, 1967-1968 (Box 43, Folder 314)
    - Miscellaneous, 1968 (Box 43, Folder 315)
    - Miscellaneous, 1968-1979 (Box 43, Folder 316)
  - Speeches, Manuscripts and Publications - Speeches, 1953-1979; 2_4
    This subseries contains texts of commencement addresses, awards acceptance speeches, eulogies, and other speeches addressing a variety of subjects.
    - Miscellaneous, 1954-1959 (Box 43, Folder 317)
      Includes list of speeches, 1953-1976.
    - Miscellaneous, 1960-1962 (Box 43, Folder 318)
    - Miscellaneous, 1963 (Box 43, Folder 319)
    - Miscellaneous, 1964 (Box 43, Folder 320)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1966 (Box 44, Folder 321)
    - Miscellaneous, 1967-1968 (Box 44, Folder 322)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969 (Box 44, Folder 323)
    - Miscellaneous, 1972 (Box 44, Folder 324)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1979 (Box 44, Folder 325)
  - Speeches, Manuscripts and Publications - Miscellaneous Papers, 1954-1975; 2_5
    - 1954-1967 (Box 44, Folder 326)
    - 1968-1971 (Box 44, Folder 327)
    - 1972-1975 (Box 44, Folder 328)
    - 1979 (Box 45, Folder 329)
- Miscellany, 1926-1982; 3
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Series 3 contains biographical information, honors and awards, and clippings. Included among the clippings is material from Harrar's college years at Oberlin. A memorial book to J. George Harrar is also included.
  - Biographical Information (Box 45, Folder 330)
  - Honors and Awards, 1953-1971 (Box 45, Folder 331)
  - Honors and Awards, 1972-1982 (Box 45, Folder 332)
    Includes memorial tributes.
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1927-1968 (Box 45, Folder 333)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1968-1975, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 334)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings - Mexico, 1969 (Box 45, Folder 335)
  - J. G. Harrar, 1906-1982 (Box 45, Folder 336)
  - Calendars, 1975, 1977 (Box 45, Folder 337)
- J. George Harrar photographs, 1926-1971; 1019; 5.26 Cubic Feet 7 document boxes and 4 flat boxes
  Biographical / Historical
  Jacob George Harrar was born in Painesville, Ohio, on December 2, 1906, to Ellwood Harrar, an engineer, and Lucetta Sternes Harrar. He attended Oberlin College from 1924 to 1928 where he majored in biology and excelled in athletics. After receiving the A.B. degree from Oberlin, Harrar continued his education at the Iowa State College of Agriculture and Mechanical Arts. He was awarded the M.S. degree in 1929 and immediately embarked on a career in teaching and agricultural research as an assistant professor at the College of Agriculture, University of Puerto Rico. Within a year Harrar became head of the department of biology. He left that position in 1934 to pursue a Ph.D. in plant pathology at the University of Minnesota. It was here he began a close personal and professional relationship with E. C. Stakman, under whom he studied. Later, in 1958, they collaborated on the book, "Principles of Plant Pathology."
  In 1935, Harrar, having achieved a doctorate degree in plant pathology, once again resumed teaching, accepting an assistant professorship at the Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Rising to full professor in 1937, Harrar remained at the Institute until 1941. From 1941 to 1942 he headed the Division of Plant Pathology and the Agricultural Experiment Station at Washington State College.
  In 1942, Harrar left academics to create and administer in Mexico the Rockefeller Foundation's first cooperative assistance program in agricultural science. With his team of American specialists, Harrar implemented a Foundation program of soil and hybrid experimentation to improve wheat and corn yields. Within a few years the Mexican program proved enormously successful and the Foundation was invited to implement the same program in Colombia, Chile, and India. Harrar is generally regarded as the father of what soon became known as "The Green Revolution."
  Harrar, in 1952, became Deputy Director for Agriculture, Division of Natural Sciences and Agriculture, of the Rockefeller Foundation. In 1955, he became Director for Agriculture organizing further projects in agricultural assistance and cooperation in all the Central American countries. He was appointed Vice President of the Foundation in 1959, and in 1961 succeeded Dean Rusk as its President. Under Harrar, the Rockefeller Foundation during the 1960s reoriented its programs to concentrate in five areas: the conquest of hunger, by improving the quantity and quality of food supplies; the solution of population problems; the strengthening of emerging centers of learning in developing nations; the provision of better educational opportunities for the disadvantaged groups in the U. S.; and the enhancement of the cultural lives of Americans.
  Retiring in 1972, Harrar was the first man ever to be appointed a Life Fellow of the Rockefeller Foundation. During the 1970s he continued his involvement as a member of such professional and scientific organizations as the National Academy of Sciences and the Nutrition Foundation. In 1980 he was awarded the Aztec Eagle Award, the highest honor bestowed by the Mexican government for service to their country by a foreign citizen. He also, during his lifetime, received numerous honors, degrees, and citations from many other foreign governments and from both American and foreign universities.
  In addition to "Strategy for the Conquest of Hunger, Selected Papers of J. George Harrar," he was the author of numerous scientific research papers in the fields of phytopathology and mycology, and many articles of general interest on world food problems, population, private philanthropy, economic development overseas, and environmental quality.
  J. George Harrar died on April 18, 1982.
  Photographs
  - Oberlin College, 1926-1928; 5 prints (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Schools, students, sports.
  - Mexico, 1942-1944; 27 prints (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Harrar family, volcanos, agriculture, farming, potatoes, granaries, festivals, Chapingo, meetings, field studies, corn, dances.
  - Chile, 1962; 19 prints (Box 4, Folder 36)
    Awards, South America, conferences, ceremonies.
  - Colombia, 1964; 43 prints (Box 4, Folder 37)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd, conferences, meetings, South America.
  - Latin America, circa 1954-1966; 34 prints (Box 4, Folder 38)
    South America, conferences, meetings, graduations, agriculture.
  - Latin America, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Families, conferences, awards, ceremonies, buildings.
  - African Schools, undated; 13 prints (Box 4, Folder 40)
    Africa, Liberia, Nigeria, Kenya, Rhodesia, Uganda. Schools, buildings, hospitals.
  - African Schools, undated; 14 prints (Box 5, Folder 41)
    Africa, Congo, Ghana, Liberia, Ethiopia. Schools, hospitals, agriculture.
  - Asian Visit, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    India, libraries, laboratories, museums, schools.
  - Asian Visit, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    India, irrigation, agriculture, wheat.
  - Japan / Phillipines (President Lyndon B. Johnson Visit), 1953; 10 prints (Box 5, Folder 44)
    Agriculture, wheat, conferences.
  - America - Award Ceremonies, 1960s (Box 5, Folder 45)
    Ceremonies, awards, dinners, graduations, Harrar family.
  - Chistmas Photos, 1960 / Dinner for Dean Rusk, February 26, 1961, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    Holidays, dinners, parties.
  - Rockefeller Foundation 50th Anniversary Dinner, 1963 April 2; 10 prints (Box 5, Folder 47)
    Dinners, speeches, parties.
  - Rockefeller Foundation 50th Anniversary Dinner, 1963 April 2 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    Dinners, parties, speeches.
  - Rockefeller Foundation 50th Anniversary Dinner, 1963 April 2 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    Dinners, parties.
  - Rockefeller Foundation 50th Anniversary Dinner, 1963 April 2 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Improving Soil Productivity, Mexican Agricultural Program of the Rockefeller Foundation (Box 1)
  - CIANO, 1 album (Box 1)
  - Cotaxtla, 1 album (Box 2)
  - Field Day, Mexico album, 1 album (Box 2)
  - Peru and Ecuador trips, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Agricultural Program for India, 1 album (Box 3)
  - Indian Agricultural Program, 1959; 1 album (Box 3)
  - All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS), 1960-1961; 1 album (Box 3)
  - Slides - South America, Guatemala, Peru, Ecuador, Uruguay, Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Cuba, Costa Rica, 1947-1952 (Box 6)
  - Slides - Mexico, Alaska, Hawaii, India, Israel, Africa, Indonesia, Thailand, Siam, and unidentified (Box 7)
  - Harrar - Portraits (Box 8)
  - Album 1, 1942; 1 album (Box 9)
  - Album 2, 1943-1950; 1 album (Box 9)
  - Album 3, 1 album (Box 10)
  - Album 4 - South America (Box 10)
  - Mexican Agricultural Program, 4 albums (Box 11)